Finding Aid for Peoples Campaign for Choice Records 1987-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Peoples Campaign for Choice Records 1987-1988
Peoples Campaign for Choice.
Organization formed to defeat 1988 Michigan ballot proposal prohibiting Medicaid funding for abortions. Campaign records, executive committee files, financial records, media materials, and consultants files; also photographs.
9442; Bt 2
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Planned Parenthood League Inc. (Donor No. 6613 ) in July and August 1993.
The record group is open for research.
In February 1987, Right to Life of Michigan, Inc. gathered signatures on petitions to initiate legislation to end Medicaid funding of abortions in Michigan in cases where the mother's life was not at risk. It submitted the signatures to the Secretary of State for validation and the Michigan legislature was then given the option to ignore, pass, or amend the initiative. The initiative could not be vetoed. The legislature chose to amend the legislation to assist state employees, but did not include an exception for victims of rape and incest. Because the pro-choice governor, James Blanchard, could not veto the legislation, P.A. 59 was passed into law.
The Planned Parenthood League, Inc. established a coalition of over forty political, social and religious organizations that supported the right to choose, called the Peoples Campaign for Choice (PCC), whose goal it became to defeat the legislation. In order to comply with campaign finance laws, PCC set up a separate organization to coordinate its fundraising, the Coalition to Protect Michigan Lives (CPML). PCC also set up an education fund to help finance the campaign with large grants.
Late in 1987, PCC began its own petition drive to get the new law on the November 1988 ballot so the people of the state could vote on the ban of Medicaid funding. Meanwhile, it also filed a court action in an attempt to prevent P.A. 59 from taking effect before the people had a chance to vote. PCC argued that the ban was an attack on the poor, mostly blacks; that the non-exception for rape and incest was unjust; that this was a step toward overruling Roe v. Wade (1973); and that it was cheaper to the taxpayer in the long run to fund the abortion rather than to raise the child on crime-ridden welfare streets.
PCC succeeded in getting the referendum on the ballot and it was titled Proposal A. Proposal A asked voters whether or not they wanted the new law which banned Medicaid funding of abortions to remain on the books. If it passed, the law would take effect; if it failed (the goal of PCC) the law would be overturned.
PCC faced an uphill battle from the beginning. Similar laws had been passed in several other states, and despite predictions from pro-choice groups, welfare spending had not increased in these states. Most importantly, Right to Life of Michigan, Inc. was very well-funded and well-organized, whereas PCC faced coalition, consulting and especially fundraising problems due to competition for donations with the presidential and U.S. Senate campaigns. PCC was still short $3/4 million in funds for its media campaign in October 1988. Nevertheless, it managed to gain strength in the polls toward November 1988, and launched a fairly-successful emergency fundraising drive, but PCC failed to get its message out.
Proposal A passed with a majority of over 470,000 votes on November 8, 1988.
The Peoples Campaign for Choice record group covers the years 1987-1988 and divides into five series: Campaign Records, Executive Committee Records, Financial Records, Media Records, Consultants Records. The PCC record group can be useful for researchers of several topics of interest including reproductive freedom history, women's issues, health care policies, and campaign planning/organization.
Subjects:
Abortion--Government policy--Citizen participation.; Elections--Michigan--1988.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Milliken, Helen W. (Helen Wallbank); Political elections--1988.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Campaign Records
  The Campaign Records series (1 linear foot) includes background research about Medicaid funding of abortions, campaign plans, field staff activities, and information about the petition drive. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Abortion service providers (Box 1)
  - Absentee ballots (Box 1)
  - Background research, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Ballot wording (Box 1)
  - Black campaign (Box 1)
  - Campaign manager reports (Box 1)
  - Campaign planning (Box 1)
  - Campaign problems (Box 1)
  - Complaint re: Right to Life of Michigan, Inc. campaign tactics (Box 1)
  - Concession statement (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Jeremy Karpatkin (Box 1)
    - Legislators (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Debate October 1988 (Box 1)
  - Detroit field office (Box 1)
  - Draft speeches (Box 1)
  - Election results (Box 1)
  - Employee contracts (Box 1)
  - Field staff (Box 1)
  - House Joint Resolution D (Box 1)
  - Job postings (Box 1)
  - Labor support (Box 1)
  - Leadership development (Box 1)
  - Legal action (Box 1)
  - Legislative research (Box 1)
  - Membership and outreach activities (Box 1)
  - Office manager (Box 1)
  - Opposition research (Box 1)
  - Peoples Campaign for Choice
    - Early establishment of (Box 1)
    - Incorporation papers and By-laws (Box 1)
    - Mission statement (Box 1)
  - Personnel policies (Box 1)
  - Petition drive
    - Background information (Box 1)
    - Challenge process (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Status reports (Box 1)
    - Validation (Box 1)
  - Precinct delegates (Box 1)
  - Questions & Answers (Box 1)
  - Religious campaign (Box 1)
  - Republican Party support (Box 1)
  - Right to Life
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Paraphernalia (pamphlets and other literature) (Box 1)
  - Staff (Box 1)
  - State agency network (Box 1)
  - Training of staff (Box 1)
  - Trip to Washington D.C. (Box 1)
- Executive Committee Records
  The Executive Committee Records series (0.5 linear foot) contains minutes and memos for the PCC executive committee and the CPML executive committee (two separate committees with many overlapping members). The series are arranged chronologically.
  - Peoples Campaign for Choice Executive Committee Minutes and Memos
    - March 1987-September 1987 (Box 1)
    - October 1987-November 1988 (Box 2)
  - Committee for the Protection of Michigan Lives Executive Committee Minutes and Memos
    - March 1987-June 1988 (Box 2)
- Financial Records
  The Financial Records series (0.5 linear foot) documents the activities of the CPML. It is the records of the financial and budget committees and the fundraising staff. It includes financial plans, fundraising event planning, and grant applications. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Bridgewalk pledges (Box 2)
  - Budget (Box 2)
  - CPML Campaign procedures (Box 2)
  - Direct mailings and solicitations (Box 2)
  - Education Fund (Box 2)
  - Emergency fundraising September-November 1988 (Box 2)
  - Finance Committee Activities (Box 2)
  - Fundraising
    - General (Box 2)
    - Plans (Box 2)
    - Reports 1987 (Box 2)
  - Grants
    - General (Box 2)
    - Lansing Constitutional Liberties Fund, Inc. (Box 2)
    - National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL) (Box 2)
  - Income/Expenses (Box 2)
  - Invoices, Murphine & Walsh (consultants) (Box 2)
  - Leases (Box 2)
  - Major donors
    - Plans (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Judy Taubman (Box 2)
  - Major events (Box 2)
  - Miller, Canfield, Paddock and Stone, bills (Box 2)
  - Phone solicitation (Box 2)
  - Post-campaign debts (Box 2)
  - Pro-Life financial records (Box 2)
  - Small events (Box 2)
- Media Records
  The Media Records series (0.5 linear foot) documents the attempts by PCC to get their message out to the voters. It includes scripts of television and radio ads, press releases, press conferences, and clippings from statewide and national newspapers and journals. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Bids from media consultants (Box 2)
  - Bush, George, radio ad controversy (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 2)
    folders 1-2
  - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 3)
    folders 3-5
  - Endorsements
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Blanchard, Governor James (Box 3)
    - Ford, Mrs. Gerald (Box 3)
    - Levin, U.S. Representative Sander (Box 3)
    - Michigan Physicians for Choice (Box 3)
    - Milliken, former Governor William and Mrs. (Box 3)
    - Wattleton, Faye, President of Planned Parenthood of America (Box 3)
  - Letters to the editor (Box 3)
  - Media budget 1988 (Box 3)
  - Media committee (Box 3)
  - Media contacts (Box 3)
  - Media coordinator training (Box 3)
  - Media plans (Box 3)
  - Media schedules (Box 3)
  - Paraphernalia (pamphlets and other literature) (Box 3)
  - Photos, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Press conferences
    - 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - June 14, 1988 (Box 3)
    - October 17, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Press information packet (Box 3)
  - Press releases
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - Undated (Box 3)
  - Press talking points (Box 3)
  - Radio ad scripts (Box 3)
  - Signature ads (Box 3)
  - Speeches (Box 3)
  - Television ad scripts (Box 3)
  - Television editorial (Box 3)
- Consulting Records
  The Consultants Records series (0.5 linear foot) is directly related to all of the other record series. The PCC hired consultants to run their petition drive, to analyze the demographics of the electorate, to develop campaign and fundraising plans and to formulate a media message and produce commercials. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - American Petition Consultants (Box 3)
  - Casey Communications (Box 3)
  - First Tuesday (Box 3)
  - Klein, Ethel (Box 3)
  - Murphine & Walsh
    - Contracts (Box 3)
    - Campaign plans June 1987-April 1988 (Box 3)
    - Catastrophe model theory (Box 3)
    - Demographic clusters (Box 3)
    - Demographics (Box 3)
    - Evaluation and action (Box 3)
    - Weekly reports #1-6 July-September 1987 (Box 3)
  - Research polling
    - Selection process (Box 3)
    - Mellman & Lazarus activities (Box 3)
    - Focus groups (Box 3)
    - Surveys
      - September 1987-March 1988, August 1988 (Box 3)
      - April 1988, 3 folders (Box 3)